E-mail: erik.exists@gmail.com Website: robotpuggle.com Github: @parenthetical-e

In Summary

In industry and academia I have worked and published in scientific machine learning, causal analysis, chemistry, nanotechnology, (computational) neuroscience, biochemistry, reinforcement learning, and biological computation. I'm a broad excellent scientist and a thoughtful software engineer.

Experience

Pasteur Labs - New York, NY

Advanced Projects Lead

2023 - Present

Team lead for advanced projects in scientific machine learning. Focus on multi-physics surrogates and casual discovery methods for industrial deployments.

Senior Scientist 2021 - 2023

Co-lead scientific machine learning research program focused on closing the performance gap between academic results and industrial requirements. Lead development of Pasteur's scientific machine learning library and training pipeline (neural operators, graph neural networks, etc; >30 models). Lead development of Pasteur's causal analysis software for physical systems and time-series. Established "simulation intelligence" methods that use physical properties to do analog computations.

Carnegie Mellon University - Pittsburgh, PA

Research Fellow (Scientist)

2018 - 2021

Developed mathematical accounts of curiosity in reinforcement learning and multi-agent systems which reframed and answered a key open question in decision science. Established a new theoretical upper limit for biological computation.

Kernel - Los Angeles, CA

Senior Scientist 2017 - 2018

Developed a model for complex spatio-temporal electrical field shaping for use in brain computer interfaces and deep brain stimulation. This project blended biophysical models with deep neural networks and led to a 400,000 fold speed-up – a key requirement for real-time use.

U.C. San Diego - San Diego, CA

Postdoctoral Fellow

2014 - 2017

Conducted theoretical and computational research on the optimal coding properties of neural oscillations. Co-lead development of a python tool to analyze electrophysiological time-series which has found widespread use in the neuroscience community and been downloaded >275,000 times.

Colorado State University - Fort Collins, CO

Graduate Research Assistant (Seger Lab)

2006 - 2012

Biosearch Technologies - Novato, CA

Research Assistant II

2004 - 2006

Optimization of high-throughput chemistry for DNA synthesis; reporter gene development (stability and kinetics).

EDUCATION

Colorado State University (Fort Collins) - Ph.D, Psychology; Masters, Psychology.

California Polytechnic State University (San Luis Obispo, CA) – B.S., Chemistry; B.S., Biochemistry; Minor, Philosophy.

Programming

Developed production-ready machine learning models in modern frameworks (jax, torch). Expert scientific programmer (python). Fluent in standard development tools (git, docker, etc).

Press

Brain's 'Background Noise' May Hold Clues to Persistent Mysteries, Quanta Magazine, 2021.

SELECT

Total citations: >2,000. H-index: 14.

PUBLICATIONS.

Peterson EJ & Lavin A, Physical Computing for Materials Acceleration Platforms, *Matter* 5, 3586-3596 (2022).

Donoghue T*, Haller M*, **Peterson EJ***, et al, Parameterizing Neural Power Spectra into Periodic and Aperiodic Components, *Nature Neuroscience* 23 1655-1665 (2020).